<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
 "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % vers   SYSTEM "version.xml">
<!ENTITY blyte "<application>Blyte</application>">
%vers;
]>

<book id="blyte-manual" lang="en">
  <title>Blyte Manual</title>

  <subtitle>Version &blyte.version;</subtitle>
  
  <bookinfo>
	
    <authorgroup>
	  <corpauthor>Oskusoft</corpauthor>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2004, October 17.</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>Oskusoft</holder>
    </copyright>

	<legalnotice><para>TODO: Insert legal stuff
	here.</para></legalnotice>
	
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>This is the manual for the &blyte; screenwriting software. This
	version of the manual corresponds to version &blyte.version; of the
	software.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Basic concepts</title>

	  <para>If you don't know anything about writing a screenplay, get a
	  copy of a book such as Trottier's "The Screenwriter's Bible". This
	  manual will not cover the same ground, but focuses on concepts
	  specific to &blyte;.</para>

	  <para>&blyte; divides a screenplay into a long list of elements,
	  each with a specific <emphasis>element style</emphasis>. The
	  available element styles are:</para>

	  <variablelist>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Scene</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Scene header. Example: "INT. MOTEL ROOM - NIGHT".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Action</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Describes action. Example: "John grabs the gun from the
			desk."</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Character</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>A speaking character's name. Example: "HARRY".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Dialogue</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Speech. Example: "You could do that, sure. On the other
			hand, if you want to live beyond the next minute or so, you
			might want to rethink your approach."</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Parenthetical</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Describes how the actor should say the following
			dialogue. Example: "(serious)".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Transition</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Describes a non-standard transition between scenes.
			Example: "DISSOLVE TO:".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Shot</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Describes an in-scene shot. Example: "THE
			NECKLACE".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Note</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Note style has a yellow background so it stands out, and
			is used to insert notes to yourself or to others about that
			part of the script. Example: "Should Bobby shoot
			first?".</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

	  </variablelist>
	  
	</sect1>

  </chapter>
  
  <chapter>
	<title>Basic usage</title>

	<para>This chapter discusses basic usage of &blyte;.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Main window</title>

	  <para>The main window has the following parts in it in top-to-bottom
	  order, after the standard menu bar:</para>

	  <variablelist>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Element style combo box</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>This shows the style of the element the cursor is
			currently positioned in and allows you to change it.</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Script tabs</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>Each script gets its own tab, with the tab's name being
			the filename of each script. You can click on each tab to
			change the active script to that one.</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Main text area</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>This is where the actual script is shown and
			edited.</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Status bars</term>
		  <listitem>

			<para>At the bottom is a three-part status bar that shows
			current page and total page count in the last section, and
			information about what the Enter/Tab keys would do in the
			first two sections.</para>
			
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
	  </variablelist>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Basic editing</title>

	  <sect2>
		<title>Moving around</title>

		<para>The usual movement keys are available: Up/Down/Left/Right to
		move around, Home/End to move to start/end of line, Page Up/Page
		Down to move up/down one page (actually one screenful), and CTRL +
		Home/End to move to start/end of script.</para>

		<para>CTRL + Up/Down moves one scene up or down.</para>
	  
	  </sect2>

	  <sect2>
		<title>Deleting elements</title>

		<para>The Delete and Backspace keys delete text one character at a
		time. They also join elements to one another if pressed at,
		respectively, at the end or at the start of an element. The joined
		element will always have the style of the preceding
		element.</para>
		
	  </sect2>

	  <sect2>
		<title>Adding elements and changing their style</title>

		<para>The Enter key will always create a new element. If the
		cursor is at the end of an element, the new element will be an
		empty one, otherwise the current element is split at the cursor
		position.</para>

		<para>The Tab key will create a new element if the cursor is at
		the end of an element, otherwise it will switch the current
		element's style. Shift + Tab will always switch the element's
		style.</para>

		<para>What kind of element Enter/Tab/Shift + Tab will
		create/switch to is dependent on the current style of the element,
		and is configurable by the user. These values for Enter/Tab are
		always shown at the bottom of the window at the status bar.
		Additionally the Tab section will have a "[change]" at the end if
		pressing Tab would switch the element's style, not create a new
		one.</para>

		<para>Other ways to change an element's style are using the combo
		box at the top of the window, or pressing a short-cut key for each
		element style. See Help/Commands for a list of the keys.</para>

		<para>Shift + Enter or CTRL + Enter will insert a forced
		linebreak.</para>
		
	  </sect2>
	  
	  <sect2>
		<title>Selecting text</title>

		<para>When selecting text, one end of the selection is always
		fixed and the other one moves around with the cursor. You can
		select text by clicking and dragging with the mouse (right-click
		unselects), or by pressing CTRL + Space which sets the fixed point
		of the selection at current position and then moving around, or by
		pressing some movement key together with Shift (e.g. Shift +
		Up).</para>

		<para>You can select the current scene with CTRL + A.</para>

		<para>After you've selected the desired text, you can the
		cut/copy/paste commands to move text around, delete it, etc. You
		can also press Del to simply delete it. Note that this is not
		undoable in any way.</para>
		
	  </sect2>

	  <sect2>
		<title>Auto-completion</title>

		<para>Auto-completion saves typing in scene/character/transition
		elements by showing a list of other elements from the script that
		match the text in the current element. For example, if you've
		written the characters "MO" in a new character element, you'll see
		a list of all character elements that start with "MO" and if you
		want, you can select one of them and that text will complete the
		current element.</para>

		<para>The auto-completion list only appears after you've written
		at least one character. If you want to see a list of all possible
		choices, write a single character and delete it.</para>

		<para>You can move around in the list with the Up/Down/Page
		up/Page down keys. Pressing Enter will complete the text and start
		a new element, while pressing End will complete the text but will
		not start a new element. Pressing ESC will make the list go
		away.</para>
		
	  </sect2>

	  <sect2>
		<title>Miscellaneous</title>

		<para>When inserting a new empty parenthetical element, "()" will
		automatically be added to it and the cursor positioned in the
		middle. Likewise, when switching a parenthetical element to
		something else, if it only contains "()", it will be replaced by
		"" (empty). If you write a "(" in an empty dialogue or character
		element if will switch to a parenthetical element. If you press
		Enter or Tab at the ending ")" to start a new element, the ")"
		will stay in the parenthetical.</para>

		<para>If you write "EXT." or "INT." (case doesn't matter) at the
		start of any element, it will switch to a scene element
		automatically.</para>
		
	  </sect2>

	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
	<title>Other commands</title>

	<para>This chapter describes commands not discussed in other
	chapters.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>File/New,open,save,save as,close,revert</title>

	  <para>These do what you'd expect them to do.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>File/Print</title>

	  <para>This opens up the current script in your configured PDF viewer
	  program, from which you can print it, or just see what it looks
	  like.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>File/Settings,load,save as</title>

	  <para>'Settings' allows you to edit the various configurable
	  settings of &blyte;. See <xref linkend="settings"/>.</para>
	  
	  <para>&blyte; loads settings from a file named "default.conf" on
	  startup. You can have as many config files as you want, and use the
	  load/save as commands to manage them.</para>

	  <para>You can give a "--conf /home/me/someother.conf" command line
	  parameter to &blyte; to have it start up with some other
	  configuration file.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Cut,Copy,Paste</title>

	  <para>Cut, copy and paste work pretty much the same way as in every
	  other program. Note that these commands only use &blyte;'s own
	  internal clipboard so can't be used for copying text to/from other
	  programs. For that, see below.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Copy to,paste from clipboard</title>

	  <para>These copy/paste text to the system wide clipboard so can be
	  used for communicating with other programs. Note that if you copy
	  text to the clipboard from &blyte;, you must keep &blyte; open until
	  you've pasted the text to the destination program.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Select scene</title>

	  <para>Select all the text of the current scene.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Find &amp; Replace</title>

	  <para>This opens a dialog allowing you to search for and possibly
	  replace text. Usually it operates on all element styles, but if you
	  press the "More" button, you can select the styles it operates on,
	  which is useful renaming a character and so on.</para>

	  <para>FIXME: document F/R keys.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Remove elements</title>

	  <para>'Remove elements' opens a dialog allowing you to select one or
	  more element styles to completely remove from the script. Be sure to
	  only do this on copies of the script, because there is no way to get
	  back the removed elements.</para>

	  <para>You can use this for e.g. removing notes before sending out
	  copies of the script, or if you want a version of the script with
	  only the dialog, only the action, or only the scene headers, or
	  whatever else you can come up with.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Edit/Show formatting</title>

	  <para>This toggles whether formatting information is shown. It
	  consists of blue lines drawn around each element, plus each line is
	  prefixed with a red marker indicating the type of the line ending
	  for that line. See fileformat.txt for information about the
	  different marker types.</para>

	  <para>When using the 'Find errors' command, if you can't figure out
	  what the error is, try switching this on to see if you have two
	  elements where you thought you only had one, or something else
	  that's not obvious in the normal display.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Script/Find next error</title>

	  <para>'Find next error' searches through the script, starting from
	  the cursor position, looking for errors. This means that to search
	  the entire script for errors you should first position the cursor at
	  the beginning of the script.</para>

	  <para>If it finds any errors, it positions the cursor on the line
	  containing the error and displays a message box detailing the error.
	  You should fix the error, back up a few lines, and activate the
	  command again to search for more errors. Alternatively, if you don't
	  want to fix the error right now, move the cursor down one line if
	  you want to search for more errors.</para>

	  <para>It can detect the following errors:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>

		  <para>Empty line, or a parenthetical element containing only
		  ().</para>
		  
		</listitem>

		<listitem>

		  <para>A character element that is not followed by a
		  parenthetical or a dialogue element.</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

		  <para>A parenthetical element that does not follow a character or
		  a dialogue element.</para>
		  
		</listitem>

		<listitem>

		  <para>A dialogue element that does not follow a character or a
			parenthetical element.</para>
		  
		</listitem>
		
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Script/Paginate</title>

	  <para>'Paginate' simply repaginates the script. You normally don't
	  need to run this if you have automatic repagination enabled, but the
	  command is available for use when automatic repagination is disabled
	  or you want immediate repagination after a large cut/paste
	  operation.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Script/Title pages</title>

	  <para>'Title pages' allows you to edit your script's title pages.
	  You can have as many title pages as you want, or none at all.</para>

	  <para>At the top of the window are add/delete/move/next buttons.
	  'Add' adds a page, 'Delete' deletes the current page, 'Move' swaps
	  the current page with the next page, and 'Next' changes the view to
	  the next page.</para>

	  <para>The strings listbox contains all text strings for the current
	  page. Select the text string you want to edit in this listbox, and
	  use the add/delete buttons to add/delete text strings.</para>

	  <para>On the right side of the listbox is a coarse preview showing
	  the approximate location of text strings on the current page, with
	  the selected text string shown in red.</para>
	  
	  <para>At the bottom of the window are the settings for the selected
	  text string. There's the text itself, the position of its upper left
	  corner as an offset from the paper's upper left corner, font, size,
	  and style. 'Centered' means that the text is centered horizontally
	  on the page.</para>

	  <para>Finally there's a 'Preview' button that you can use to get an
	  accurate preview of all of the title pages.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Script/Headers</title>

	  <para>'Headers' allows you to edit your script's headers. Headers
	  are lines that are automatically added to the top of each page of
	  the script, excluding title pages and the first page of the actual
	  script.</para>
	  
	  <para>Topmost in the window is a setting for how many empty lines
	  you want inserted after your header lines.</para>
	  
	  <para>After that is a listbox of all the strings in your headers.
	  Select the text string you want to edit in this listbox, and use the
	  add/delete buttons to add/delete text strings.</para>
	  
	  <para>Below the listbox are the settings for the selected string.
	  You can adjust the string text, style, alignment, line and
	  positioning.</para>

	  <para>The text is first positioned according to the alignment
	  setting, and then its horizontal starting position is adjusted by
	  the number of characters given in 'X offset'. Note that this
	  parameter can be negative, so for example, if you want your header
	  string to start 2 characters before the left margin, select
	  'Alignment: Left' and 'X offset: -2'.</para>
	  
	  <para>Any occurrences of '${PAGE}' in the text string will be
	  replaced by the page number in the actual headers.</para>
	  
	  <para>Finally there's a 'Preview' button that you can use to get an
	  accurate preview of your headers.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Tools/Name database</title>

	  <para>'Name database' opens a window allowing you browse and search
	  through a database of more than 200,000 character names, each name
	  being categorized by its nationality and sex.</para>

	  <para>On the left side of the window is a list of the name
	  categories. The main groups available are nationalities, but there
	  are some other interesting groups, e.g. Shakespeare, Medieval,
	  Flowers etc.</para>
	  
	  <para>Select the groups you want to search in, either a single one
	  by simply clicking on it, or multiple ones by holding down CTRL and
	  then clicking on multiple items. If you want to go back to the
	  default of having all the groups selected, press the 'Select all'
	  button at the bottom of the list.</para>
	  
	  <para>On the upper right side of the window are the other search
	  parameters. There's a text box in which you can write the text you
	  want to search for, and two radio button groups.</para>
	  
	  <para>The first one affects how your search string is used. The
	  string has to match either a) at the start of the name, b) anywhere
	  in the name or c) at the end of the name.</para>
	  
	  <para>The second one selects whether male/female/both names are
	  included in the search results.</para>
	  
	  <para>The search is always case-insensitive, and a blank search
	  string matches all names.</para>
	  
	  <para>After having set all the search parameters, press the 'Search'
	  button, at which point the results list will change to contain only
	  the names matching the search parameters. A count of the matching
	  names is shown at the bottom of the window.</para>

	  <para>You can select names from the result list and press 'Insert'
	  to insert that name at your script at the current cursor
	  position.</para>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Tools/Character map</title>

	  <para>'Character map' opens a window allowing you to insert any
	  character from the supported ISO-8859-1 (i.e. Latin-1) character set
	  into your script.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Tools/Compare scripts</title>

	  <para>You need two different versions of the same script open to use
	  'Compare scripts'. Select the older one as the first script and the
	  newer one as the second script. &blyte; then goes through the
	  scripts looking for changes between them and displays the results as
	  a PDF file.</para>

	  <para>The PDF file contains only changed parts of the script. The
	  changes are color coded: Deleted lines are red, added lines are
	  green, non-changed lines (shown for context) are white, and marker
	  lines for single-line changes are yellow. The changed parts are
	  separated by two gray lines.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Help/Commands</title>

	  <para>'Commands' opens a window showing all the keyboard
	  commands.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Help/Manual</title>

	  <para>'Manual' opens this manual you're reading right now.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Help/License</title>

	  <para>The license submenu contains three commands for dealing with
	  licenses:</para>

	  <variablelist>
		
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Information</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Shows information about the current license.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Update</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Opens a file dialog allowing you to load a new
			license.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Release</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Releases your license, i.e. goes back to evaluation
			  mode.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
	  </variablelist>
	  
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
	  <title>Help/About</title>

	  <para>'About' opens the about screen for &blyte;, showing
	  information such as the version and the date this version was
	  released on.</para>
	  
	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="settings">
	<title>Settings</title>

	<para>FIXME: describe settings.</para>
	
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter>
	<title>Import and export</title>

	<para>This chapter discusses the import/export support of the
	program.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Import</title>

	  <para>Existing screenplays can currently be imported from only one
	  file format: as formatted ASCII text. The following section
	  documents the format these files should have for optimal import
	  processing.</para>
	
	  <sect2>
		<title>ASCII Text files</title>
	  
		<para>ASCII text files should have the following
		  characteristics:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  
		  <listitem>
		  
			<para>Each element style should begin at a unique column. An
			exception is that Scene and Action can begin at the same
			column.</para>

			<para>There should only be one such starting column per
			element style, i.e. all dialogue should begin at the same
			column, it shouldn't sometimes start at column 25, sometimes
			at 27, etc.</para>
		  
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>

			<para>No production markings, e.g. scene numbers, page
			numbers, cast lists, or anything like that.</para>
		  
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>

			<para>Elements should be separated by a single empty
			line.</para>
		  
		  </listitem>
		
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Below is a short example of the kind of format best
		recognized by &blyte;.</para>
		
		<screen>
EXT. OCEAN - NIGHT

The package hits the water and is submerged. A few seconds
later, a rapidly inflating liferaft appears.

The people land into the water in their parachutes. They
dispose of them and swim toward the liferaft.

INT. LIFERAFT - NIGHT

They're all aboard, taking off their clothes. When they're
all naked, Sarah gathers the wet clothes, throws them out,
and closes the entrance to the tent-like liferaft. The men
openly admire Sarah's body, as she opens a storage locker
and takes out dry clothes for everyone which they then put
on.

                      KEVIN
          I know a great way to warm up.

                      SARAH
          Sorry, I got over the "older men"
          thing a while back.

                      KEVIN
          Anytime you have a flashback, let
          me know.

Something starts beeping.
		</screen>
	  </sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Export</title>

	  <para>You can export the script as a PDF file or as a formatted
	  ASCII text file. Both are found in the File/Export dialog, which
	  allows you to choose which one to export as. If you export as a text
	  file, &blyte; will ask whether you want the page markers included or
	  not. If you're planning on importing the script to some other
	  program, you shouldn't include them, otherwise you probably
	  should.</para>
	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter>
	<title>Reports</title>

	<para>This chapter discusses the various report types &blyte; can
	generate.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Dialogue chart</title>

	  <para>'Dialogue chart' first opens a window allowing you to specify
	  what to include in the generated chart. The 'Sorted by:' options
	  select what orderings to include, while the 'Characters appearing on
	  a single page' option, if unselected, leaves out all characters
	  appearing on a single page only from the generated chart. It's
	  useful for long scripts that have many such characters, or otherwise
	  if you want to concentrate on the more important characters.</para>

	  <para>It then generates a chart in PDF format with one page for each
	  selected ordering and shows that.</para>

	  <para>The chart has two axes: The horizontal one, with page numbers
	  increasing from left to right, and the vertical one, with characters
	  ordered by the current page's sort criterion from top to
	  bottom.</para>

	  <para>If a character speaks on a given page, he will have a black
	  mark on that page's position on the chart.</para>

	  <para>Every other line has a light gray background to allow easier
	  visual matching of distant markings to character names.</para>

	  <para>You can use this chart in many ways. For example, you can at a
	  glance see if one of your side characters disappears for 50 pages in
	  the middle of the script, whether the villain is introduced too
	  late, and so on.</para>

	  <para>At the top is another chart, this one showing the dialogue
	  density for each page. Dialogue density is calculated as "number of
	  dialogue/character/parenthetical lines on page divided by total
	  number of non-empty lines on page". By looking at the chart you can
	  easily see where the action scenes are by the lower dialogue density
	  in those pages.</para>
	  
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Character report</title>

	  <para>'Character report' first opens a window allowing you to
	  specify what to include in the generated report. You can select what
	  characters are included, and what kind of information to include for
	  each character:</para>

	  <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Basic information</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Total number of speeches, total number of lines, the
			percentage of all the dialogue lines in the script that this
			character speaks (i.e. 25% would mean this character has
			one-fourth of the total dialogue in the script), average
			number of lines per speech, total words, average number of
			words per speech and average number of characters per word.
			</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Page list</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Number of pages this character speaks on, followed by a
			list of all of those pages.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Location list</term>
		  <listitem>
			<para>A list of all the locations this character speaks in,
			preceded by the number of lines spoken at each
			location.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		
	  </variablelist>

	  <para>It then generates a report in PDF format containing the
	  selected information and opens that file.</para>
	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>
</book>
