<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
 "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % vers   SYSTEM "version.xml">
<!ENTITY blyte "<application>Blyte</application>">
%vers;
]>

<book id="blyte-manual" lang="en">
  <title>Blyte User's Manual</title>

  <subtitle>Version &blyte.version;</subtitle>
  
  <bookinfo>
	
    <authorgroup>
	  <corpauthor>Oskusoft</corpauthor>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>2004, August 22.</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>Oskusoft</holder>
    </copyright>

	<legalnotice><para>Blaa blaa blaa, do not distribute
		etc.</para></legalnotice>
	
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>This is the manual for the &blyte; screenwriting software. This
	  version of the manual corresponds to version &blyte.version; of the
	  software.</para>
	
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
	<title>Basic usage</title>

	<para>This chapter discusses the basic usage of the program.</para>

  </chapter>

  <chapter>
	<title>Importing existing screenplays</title>

	<para>Existing screenplays can be imported in two formats: as
	formatted ASCII text, or as RTF files. The following sections document
	the format these files should have for optimal import
	processing.</para>
	
	<sect1>
	  <title>ASCII Text files</title>
	  
	  <para>ASCII text files should have the following
	  characteristics:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
		  
		  <para>Each element style should begin at a unique column. An
		  exception is that Scene and Action can begin at the same
		  column.</para>

		  <para>There should only be one such starting column per element
		  style, i.e. all dialogue should begin at the same column, it
		  shouldn't sometimes start at column 25, sometimes at 27,
		  etc.</para>
		  
		</listitem>

		<listitem>

		  <para>No production markings, e.g. scene numbers, page numbers,
			cast lists, or anything like that.</para>
		  
		</listitem>

		<listitem>

		  <para>Elements should be separated by a single empty
		  line.</para>
		  
		</listitem>
		
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <para>Below is a short example of the kind of format best recognized
	  by the program.</para>
	  
	  <screen>
EXT. OCEAN - NIGHT

The package hits the water and is submerged. A few seconds
later, a rapidly inflating liferaft appears.

The people land into the water in their parachutes. They
dispose of them and swim toward the liferaft.

INT. LIFERAFT - NIGHT

They're all aboard, taking off their clothes. When they're
all naked, Sarah gathers the wet clothes, throws them out,
and closes the entrance to the tent-like liferaft. The men
openly admire Sarah's body, as she opens a storage locker
and takes out dry clothes for everyone which they then put
on.

                      KEVIN
          I know a great way to warm up.

                      SARAH
          Sorry, I got over the "older men"
          thing a while back.

                      KEVIN
          Anytime you have a flashback, let
          me know.

Something starts beeping.
</screen>
	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter>
	<title>Reports</title>

	<para>This chapter discusses the various report types &blyte; can
	  generate.</para>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Dialogue chart</title>
	  <para>jep jep.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	  <title>Character report</title>
	  <para>oh yeah.</para>
	</sect1>
	
  </chapter>
</book>
